<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The coppie of a letter from major Generall Poines his quarters of the taking of Scarborough. With the coppie of the 12 articles agreed and concluded upon the 22. of Iuly, 1645. between the Honourable Sir Matthew Boynton, Knight and Baronet, one of the militarie committee, for the Northerne Association. And Sir Hugh Cholmneley Knight and Baronet, governour of that castle there, concerning the delivering of the same. As also a list of what was taken in Scarborough. Printed, and published according to order.</title>
            <author>Hopkinson, James, fl. 1645.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1645</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 9 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86552</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2756</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E294_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200185</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860990</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860990</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113117</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86552)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113117)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 48:E294[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The coppie of a letter from major Generall Poines his quarters of the taking of Scarborough. With the coppie of the 12 articles agreed and concluded upon the 22. of Iuly, 1645. between the Honourable Sir Matthew Boynton, Knight and Baronet, one of the militarie committee, for the Northerne Association. And Sir Hugh Cholmneley Knight and Baronet, governour of that castle there, concerning the delivering of the same. As also a list of what was taken in Scarborough. Printed, and published according to order.</title>
                  <author>Hopkinson, James, fl. 1645.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Alsop, and J. Coe.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1645.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on page 2: Ja. Hopkinson.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scarborough (England) --  History.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113117:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <p>THE COPPIE OF A LETTER From Major Generall <hi>Poines</hi> his quarters of the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of SCARBOROVGH.</p>
            <p>With the Coppie of the 12 Articles agreed and Concluded upon the 22. of <hi>Iuly,</hi> 1645. between the Honourable Sir <hi>Matthew Boynton,</hi> Knight and Baronet, one of the Millitarie Committee, for the Northerne Aſſociation.</p>
            <p>And Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmniley</hi> Knight and Baronet, Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Caſtle there, concerning the Delivering of the ſame.</p>
            <p>As alſo a Liſt of What was taken in SCARBOROVGH.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed, and publiſhed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>B. Alſop,</hi> and <hi>J. Coe.</hi> 1645.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:113117:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:113117:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <head>ARTICLES CORCERNING The ſurrendring of <hi>SCARBOROVGH</hi> and <hi>POMFRACT</hi> Caſtle, SENT IN A LETTER <hi>To a Gentleman of note living in the old</hi> Jury, <hi>Iuly</hi> 28, 1645.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">S</seg>Onne <hi>Thomas,</hi> I pray God bleſſe you and keep you in all your actions; Theſe are to let you underſtand, I received your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters dated the 15 of this inſtant, and two books; for the which I thanke you: alſo ſince another Letter dated the 17 of this inſtant. For newes here, after ſo long and tedious a ſiege, it pleaſed God to deliver pomefract Caſtle into our hands upon Munday laſt, I was in it my ſelfe on Tueſday, and truly it is a very ſtrong hold; If they had had but proviſion, it had been impoſsible to have taken it. The enemy was to march to Newark with Drums and Colours, and 200 Muskettiers, but no Officer to have more then what was really their owne, to carry no more then is portable; there is great riches left therein: And Generall
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:113117:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
               <hi>Poynes</hi> tooke this courſe, hee ſent the enemies with a ſtrong guard, and appointed one Captaine or Officer of every Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment to keep the Caſtle, and to prize all things in it, and ſo to be ſold, and the owners of any goods that is in it to have the firſt proffer; and ſo himſelfe drew off all the reſt of the Armie that night, and marched to <hi>Sandall</hi> Caſtle, and ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned it, but they are very ſtiffe, and will not yeeld it, ſo I carried three battering peeces to it, and am about ſending more to beat it about their eares: Alſo this day is <hi>Scarbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough Caſtle</hi> yeelded, I have ſent you here encloſed the copie of the Articles <hi>verbatim,</hi> ſo I will ſay no more of that, but referre you to them. God knowes they have been two trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome pieces of work, I am ſure they have made me many an ill nights work, and day, and now we are for other Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, ſo that my paines and care is never at an end, the Lord enable me to goe through it, as he hath wonderfully done hitherto, his holy Name be praiſed for it.</p>
            <p>I would deſire you to ſend me down a pot of ſalve for my legge, for healing and cleanſing of it, and you ſhall heare more of the effect of it afterwards. Thus being glad to heare of your health and welfare, being the onely joy your Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and I hath in this world, with our praiers to God to continue his bleſſing upon You and us all, deſiring to heare from you by the next Poſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>I reſt your ever loving Father, till death,</hi> JA. HOPKINSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="articles_of_agreement">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113117:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>Articles agreed and Conclded upon the <hi>22.</hi> of <hi>Iuly, 1645.</hi> betweene the Honourable, Sir <hi>Mathew Binton,</hi> Knight and Baronet one of the Military Committee for the Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Aſſociation, Colonell <hi>Francis Laſhells</hi> Colonell <hi>Simon Needham</hi> Commanders in in Chiefe of the Forces, for the Forces for the King and Parliament, in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and the Honourable Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmnely</hi> Kn. and Barronet Governour of the Caſtle there concerning the redention thereof to the pearſons afore mentioned.</head>
            <p n="1">I. THat the Caſtle be ſurrendred upon Friday nex be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing 25 of this inſtant July by 12. of the Clocke at none, that all the Armes, Ordnance, Ammunition and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions and goods of what ſort Soever now in and about the Caſtle except what is herafter excepted, ſhall be ſafely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113117:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
the Commander in chiefe in Scarborough, or to whom they ſhall appoint to the uſe of the King and Parliament.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That all priſoners now in the Caſtle be ſet at liberty within ſix houres after the ſealing of theſe Articles.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the Governour Sir <hi>Hugh Cholmley</hi> and thoſe Officers, Gentlemen and Souldiers, who deſire it, ſhall have a ſafe convoy from hence into Holland, or ſafely convoyed to Newark whither they ſhall chuſe, and if any after their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Newark, ſhall then reſolve to goe into Holland, giving notice thereof within ſix dayes to the Committee, then to take ſhipping at Hull; Scarborough, or Burlington key, to be accommodated paying uſuall rates, ſo that they take the firſt opportunity of wind and ſhipping, and ſuch others who deſire them, ſhall have paſſes from the ſaid Committee, to goe to the Kings Army, or any of his Garriſons as they pleaſe; not travelling above twenty in a company, where the Governour, or a Colonell ſhall be in perſon: otherwiſe not above ten in a company; the time to be limited in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall paſſes, as the diſtance of the place they goe to ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, none of them paſsing through any Garriſon of the King and Parliament, if there be any other way.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That no perſon whatſoever going from this Caſtle, be plundered, arreſted, or ſtaid upon any ground or pretence whatſoever, and in a caſe upon complaint made to the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Committee at Yorke, to be ſpeedily redreſt.</p>
            <p n="5">5. That the ſaid <hi>Cholmely</hi> ſhall have liberty to live at her owne houſe in Whitbee, and enjoy ſuch of his eſtate as is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by Ordinance of Parliament, that ſhe may have two
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113117:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
men ſervants, and two horſes to carry her ſelfe and ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary things as ſhall be granted her.</p>
            <p n="6">6. That all inferiour Officers, Commananders, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers who deſire to live at home, ſhall have paſſes granted them for that end, and ſhall not be forced to take up Armes againſt their minds, that the ſick and wounded ſhall be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided for untill their recovery, and the paſſes to travell to what place they pleaſe, having ſufficient time allowed them for their journey, and two perſons committed to take care on them.</p>
            <p n="7">7. That the Governour march on his owne horſe with Sword, Piſtols, Carbine, and defenſive Armes, and all field Officers upon their own horſes, with their Swords and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtols. All Captains whatſoever, Lievtenants and Cornets of horſe; in like manner three ſervants of the Governours, and for every field officer, as aforeſaid; and all other officers and ſouldiers whatſoever on foot without any other Armes but their ſwords: and not to be compelled to march above ten miles a day.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That all Officers and Souldiers may carry with them what is really their own, that nothing be carryed in cloth-bags or ſnapſacks but their own wearing apparell, writings, evidences, or bills.</p>
            <p n="9">9. That every Officer Gentleman and Clergy-man may have liberty to buy or lawfully procure a travelling horſe for himſelfe, and his ſervant, that all ſick and lame men may enjoy the ſame priviledge.</p>
            <p n="10">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:113117:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->10 That all Gentlemen of qualitie and Clergie men, have libertie to march, Gentlemen with their ſwords, but none of them carry above the value of 5. <abbr>l.</abbr> in monie or plate about their perſons, and nothing in their cloake-bags but as is expreſſed in the 8. Article.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That there be no fraud, deceit, whatſoever in ſpoiling or imbezeling any thing before mentioned or comprized in theſe Articles; and if any of them ſhall be violated, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie offending ſhall be delivered to the Commander in chiefe, where the fact ſhall be done, to give ſatisfaction for his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and his particular act ſhall not be underſtood as a breach of theſe Articles, nor bee prejudiciall to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>That the Garriſon and all therein be ſurrendred to the Parliament. There were about 200 in the Caſtle, and 100 came in to the Parliament. There was taken in the Caſtle of Scarborough; <hi>viz.</hi> Five braſſe Peeces of Ordnance, 30 Iron peeces of Ordnance ſome Field peeces 1000. Armes a great quantitie of Powder, Match, Bullets, and other Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munition, all Cholmleyes bag and baggage.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Hugh Cholmley.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
